<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Ide on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
        <link>https://preslav.me/tags/ide/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Ide on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 22:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/ide/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Bought a Year-Long License for GoLand</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2019/08/29/goland-license/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/08/29/goland-license/</guid>
            <description>NOTE: This is not a paid product endorsement. I&amp;rsquo;m just a happy customer. I have recently bought a full license of GoLand for a year. The trial served me well for a few months, but the IDE shutting down automatically after every 30 minutes of work, became way too annoying. I know, I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t rely on an IDE for writing Go, when VS Code or Vim would have worked just fine.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<h5 id="note-this-is-not-a-paid-product-endorsement-i-m-just-a-happy-customer">NOTE: This is not a paid product endorsement. I&rsquo;m just a happy customer.</h5>

<p>I have recently bought a full license of <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/go/">GoLand</a> for a year. The trial served me well for a few months, but the IDE shutting down automatically after every 30 minutes of work, became way too annoying. I know, I shouldn&rsquo;t rely on an IDE for writing Go, when VS Code or Vim would have worked just fine. It&rsquo;s just that the entire experience of writing, and more importantly, refactoring Go code in GoLand is so amazing.</p>

<p>Picking up a JetBrains product when coming to Go was a natural move. As a Java developer, I have used IntelliJ Idea for years. I am used to much of the refactoring goodness, and know most of the available key shortcuts by heart, so switching literally took me a minute. This one is a big plus, and JetBrains deserves a big thanks for it. Knowing that developers often switch platforms, offering the same experience everywhere is nothing short of great. I know, I know, in reality, those &ldquo;IDE&rdquo;s are nothing other than platform-specific plugins that run in the same core. One gets a similar experience when installing various officially-supported plugins for say, Visual Studio Code.</p>

<p>Almost. The official language support plugin for Go in VS Code uses much of the available open-source tooling for Go, developed by the community. While this is great, it also presents a temporary drawback. A large portion of the tooling still relies on projects using <code>GOPATH</code> and need to be updated in order to support Go modules. Since all of my projects have used Go modules from the start, I have experienced issues doing even basic refactoring in VS Code (e.g. renaming across the project)</p>

<p>The transition is happening and will sooner or later be no longer a problem. Luckily, GoLand does not seem to suffer from much of this, because it uses a different mechanism of indexing and analyzing code. I think that I&rsquo;ll stick to it for a year while community tooling gets to a stage, where modules are fully supported.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
