<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 22:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>This Week I Learned</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/04/18/this-week-i-learned/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/04/18/this-week-i-learned/</guid>
      <description>This Week I Learned (TWIL) is a weekly selection of interesting things and links I found useful during the week.
Apps and Tools  @media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   goulinkh/podcast-cli  CLI podcast player. Contribute to goulinkh/podcast-cli development by creating an account on GitHub. https://github.com |  Created with NoEmbed    @media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   ‎Data Jar  ‎Data Jar is a data store designed to be used with Shortcuts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: Developer Hegemony: The Future of Labor</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/04/15/quote-developer-hegemony-the-future-of-labor/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/04/15/quote-developer-hegemony-the-future-of-labor/</guid>
      <description>A quote from the amazing book &amp;ldquo;Developer Hegemony&amp;rdquo; (Buy on Amazon) by Erik Dietrich:
 You need to stop viewing yourself as a software engineer II or a QA specialist or a dev manager. You need to stop viewing yourself as an employee of your (or any) company and start viewing yourself as the owner of your personal brand and operation. You are an island. You are other.
 How many of you, dear readers think this way?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: The Case for Apple to Postpone macOS 10.16 into 2021 </title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/04/01/quote-the-case-for-apple-to-postpone-macos-10-16-into-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/04/01/quote-the-case-for-apple-to-postpone-macos-10-16-into-2021/</guid>
      <description>With so many errors reported throughout the lifetime of macOS Catalina, it kind of makes sense for Apple to slow down a bit and work on polishing it. Moving towards new features without fixing the existing bugs might be disastrous for the macOS ecosystem. But again, that&amp;rsquo;s Apple we&amp;rsquo;re talkign about. Anything can be expected from Apple. Like, deprecating macOS altogether, and eventually, replacing it with some some sort of iOS hybrid.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: The President Is Trapped</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/30/quote-the-president-is-trapped/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 10:38:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/30/quote-the-president-is-trapped/</guid>
      <description>Here is a quote from:
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   The President Is Trapped  Trump is utterly unsuited to deal with this crisis, either intellectually or temperamentally. https://www.theatlantic.com |  Created with NoEmbed     The president will try to blame someone else—but in this case the “someone else” is a virus, not a Mexican immigrant or a reporter with a disability, not a Muslim or a Clinton, not a dead war hero or a family of a fallen soldier, not a special counsel or an NFL player who kneels for the national anthem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This Week in Social Distancing</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/29/this-week-in-social-distancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 21:36:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/29/this-week-in-social-distancing/</guid>
      <description>This post is a sort of a time capsule. An attempt to journal my thoughts at this particular point in time. Despite the seemingly rough first part, I want it to have a hopeful message. I think that now is the time to re-align our principles, and set new trajectories.
Everywhere around the world, things are still developing faster than anyone had expected. More and more people getting infected, sick, and some, eventually dying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stay the F*** Home, Germany!</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/20/stay-the-f-home-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:28:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/20/stay-the-f-home-germany/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR: This is not a drill! Despite the seemingly low moratilty rate in Germany, nearly 3000 people might die by the end of April alone. We can help keep many of them alive.
Judging by how much people in Munich seem to enjoy the sunny days of spring, I am going to conclude that either:
 they all live in complete denial of the situation they already gave up they fully trust that no matter what happens, the German healthcare system would fix them in no time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Step Outside the Comfort Zone</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/14/a-step-outside-the-comfort-zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 17:36:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/14/a-step-outside-the-comfort-zone/</guid>
      <description>Yes, the current situation sucks. Big time. It&amp;rsquo;s not good for anyone. Least of all, for the ones fighting for their lives, and those, doing their best to bring things back to normal. It needs patience and coordinated effort, but we&amp;rsquo;ll make it through, sooner or later. Patience and perseverance are hard, I know, but those are what has kept humanity moving forward. They would do so, for generations to come.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elixir-Style Actors in Go</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/07/elixir-style-actors-in-golang/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 17:04:29 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/07/elixir-style-actors-in-golang/</guid>
      <description>My foray into Elixir brought forward many more similarities between it and Go, than I originally expected. One of them is how both handle concurrency. With respect to that, creating Elixir-style stateful actors in Go is surprisingly easy. Answering the question, whether one needs them, or can make use of them, I’d leave to the user. If you approach me back saying that the same thing can be achieved using a channel or a map with sync.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use the Git History to Identify Pain Points in Any Project</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/01/use-the-git-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 17:50:14 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/01/use-the-git-history/</guid>
      <description>Have you heard of Adam Tornhill&amp;rsquo;s work? If not, I highly recommend that you set some time aside and check out Your Code as a Crime Scene or Software DEsign X-Rays. In both books, the author dives into a bit of an unexplored territory - looking at the evolution of a codebase as a factor of its changes over time.
Much of the tooling we use to mitigate tech debt is preventive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEx Is Dope!</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/24/iex-is-dope/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 07:45:20 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/24/iex-is-dope/</guid>
      <description>iEx (Elixir&amp;rsquo;s interactive shell) is pure dope! It helped bring my development efforts back to the &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s play and see what happens&amp;rdquo; level. Since Elixir modules are stateless and made up of pure functions, reloading a module is as easy as calling r MyModule inside iEx. During development, I&amp;rsquo;d try to keep one module called Demo, or Scratch, etc, where I&amp;rsquo;d do the quick and dirty setting up of things. This scratch module would usually have one function only, called demo or run.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>