<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
        <link>https://preslav.me/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 10:28:44 +0100</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://preslav.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Posts</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/post/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 10:28:44 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/post/</guid>
            <description></description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Projects</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/projects/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 06:29:15 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/projects/</guid>
            <description></description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Microblogs</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/</guid>
            <description></description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Hi there 👋🏼</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/about/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2018 06:29:15 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/about/</guid>
            <description>Preslav Rachev   Follow @preslavrachev    I am a software engineer with around a decade behind my back, developing data-intensive software systems and backend applications. I am currently a part of KI labs’ diverse team of data and software-aficionados. Besides my pure developer duties, I advocate for a strong culture among developers - whether through this blog, or speaking at various events.
I am an avid reader, a distance runner, and a hobby musician.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div
    style="display: flex; justify-content:space-between; align-items:center; margin-bottom: 1rem; width: 100%; font-family: sans-serif;">
    <div style="display: flex; align-items:center">
        <img src="/images/avatar.jpg"
            class="ba b--black-10 db br-100 w2 w3-ns h2 h3-ns"
            style="width: 8rem; border-radius: 100%" />
        <div style="display:flex; flex-direction:column; margin-left: 1rem;">
            <div style="font-weight: bold">Preslav Rachev</div>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div style="vertical-align:middle">
        <a href="https://twitter.com/preslavrachev?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"
            class="twitter-follow-button" data-size="large"
            data-show-screen-name="false" data-show-count="false">Follow
            @preslavrachev</a>
        <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"
            charset="utf-8"></script>
    </div>
</div>

<p>I am a software engineer with around a decade behind my back, developing
data-intensive software systems and backend applications. I am currently a part
of <a href="https://www.ki-labs.com/">KI labs’</a> diverse team of data and
software-aficionados. Besides my pure developer duties, I advocate for a strong
culture among developers - whether through this blog, or speaking at various
events.</p>

<p>I am an avid reader, a distance runner, and a hobby musician.</p>

<p>Being a genuinely curious individual, I always keep an eye on challenging
problems I could help solve. If yours is one of those, <a href="/contact/">I’d love to hear from
you</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Projects</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/projects_old/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2018 06:29:15 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/projects_old/</guid>
            <description>.grid { display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; } .card-wrapper { width: 50%; padding: 0.2rem; } @media (max-width: 960px) { .card-wrapper { width: 100%; } } .card { border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; border-radius: 8px; } .card a { text-decoration: none; }  What follows is a small showcase of applications, I have worked on over the past years and I am really proud sharing. Get in touch with me, if you&amp;rsquo;d like to dsicuss them further.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<style scoped>
  .grid {
    display: flex;
    flex-wrap: wrap;
  }

  .card-wrapper {
    width: 50%;
    padding: 0.2rem;
  }

  @media (max-width: 960px) {
    .card-wrapper {
      width: 100%;
    }
  }

  .card {
    border: 1px solid #d4d4d4;
    border-radius: 8px;
  }

  .card a {
    text-decoration: none;
  }
</style>

<p>What follows is a small showcase of applications, I have worked on over the past
years and I am really proud sharing. <a href="/contact">Get in touch with me</a>, if you&rsquo;d
like to dsicuss them further.</p>

<div class="grid" style="display:none">
  <div class="card-wrapper">
    <div class="card" style="display: flex; flex-direction: column">
      <div class="image-container">
        <img src="/images/projects/mixtape.jpg" alt=""
          style="width: 100%; height: 200px; object-fit: cover;">
      </div>
      <div class="title">

        <div class="card-content" style="padding: 1rem">
          <h2><a href="">Mixtape</a></h2>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="card-wrapper">
    <div class="card">
      B
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="card-wrapper">
    <div class="card">
      C
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

<ul>
<li><a href="#mixtape"><strong>Mixtape:</strong></a> Go beyond the boundaries of the single podcast.
Discover and mix
podcast content around your favorite topics.</li>
<li><a href="#noembed"><strong>NoEmbed:</strong></a> A great preview is worth a thousand links.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="mixtape-https-mixtape-preslav-me"><a href="https://mixtape.preslav.me/">Mixtape</a></h2>

<p><a href="https://mixtape.preslav.me/">Mixtape</a> is a search engine for podcast content.
It stands out from the rest, because of its <em>focus on episodes, rather than
entire feeds</em>. Just like mixtapes in the old days, it allows listeners to search
and subscribe to topics of interests, rather than to separate feeds. It also
allows audio enthusiasts to pick and share particular audio clips with friends.
Something like this:</p>

<iframe
  src="https://mixtape.preslav.me/episode/d0901898/embed?start=00:07:21&stop=00:07:39"
  scrolling="no" width="400" height="300"
  style="border:none; margin: 0px auto; display: block"></iframe>

<h2 id="noembed-https-noembed-preslav-me"><a href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></h2>

<p><a href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a> is an easy way to create engaging URL
previews from every link - even when the underlying site does not provide the
necessary metadata. NoEmbed strives to be smart, fast, and WYSIWYG - there are
no hidden ads, or suspicious analytics on behalf of end users. API consumers get
only what they paid for - engaging URL previews.</p>

<div style="font-size: 0.8rem">
  




<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%; margin-bottom: 1rem">

  
  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex:1; background: url(https://images.unsplash.com/uploads/141103282695035fa1380/95cdfeef?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;ixid=eyJhcHBfaWQiOjEyMDd9&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;q=80); background-size:cover; background-position:center; min-height: 120px">
  </div>
  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://noembed.preslav.me">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        NoEmbed: Create rich URL embeds, even when sites don&#39;t support oEmbed.</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      NoEmbed uses performant and state-of-the-art technology to extract website information and present it in a format easy to embed and share</div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me">https://noembed.preslav.me | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title></title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/random/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/random/</guid>
            <description>  var x = new XMLHttpRequest(); x.open(&#34;GET&#34;, &#34;/sitemap.xml&#34;, true); x.onreadystatechange = function () { if (x.readyState == 4 &amp;&amp; x.status == 200) { const doc = x.responseXML; const locs = doc.getElementsByTagName(&#34;loc&#34;); const links = [] for (idx in locs) { links.push(locs[idx].textContent); } const randomLink = links[Math.round(Math.random() * links.length)] document.location.href = randomLink; } }; x.send(null);    Randomness ensues ...  </description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html>

<head>
    <script type="text/javascript">
        var x = new XMLHttpRequest();
        x.open("GET", "/sitemap.xml", true);
        x.onreadystatechange = function () {
            if (x.readyState == 4 && x.status == 200) {
                const doc = x.responseXML;
                const locs = doc.getElementsByTagName("loc");
                const links = []
                for (idx in locs) {
                    links.push(locs[idx].textContent);
                }

                const randomLink = links[Math.round(Math.random() * links.length)]
                document.location.href = randomLink;
            }
        };
        x.send(null);
    </script>
</head>

<body>
    Randomness ensues ...
</body>

</html>]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Contact 🤙🏼</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/contact/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/contact/</guid>
            <description>Want to get in touch? No problem! Find me on Twitter. Follow right away or send me a direct message. I am also on GitHub, Medium, and LinkedIn.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Want to get in touch? No problem! Find me on <a href="https://twitter.com/preslavrachev">Twitter</a>. Follow right away or send me a direct message. I am also on <a href="https://github.com/preslavrachev">GitHub</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/@preslavrachev">Medium</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/preslavrachev/">LinkedIn</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Privacy Policy</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/privacy/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/privacy/</guid>
            <description>At Random Bits of Wisdom, accessible from https://preslav.me, one of our main priorities is the privacy of our visitors. This Privacy Policy document contains types of information that is collected and recorded by Random Bits of Wisdom and how we use it.
If you have additional questions or require more information about our Privacy Policy, do not hesitate to contact us.
This Privacy Policy applies only to our online activities and is valid for visitors to our website with regards to the information that they shared and/or collect in Random Bits of Wisdom.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Random Bits of Wisdom, accessible from https://preslav.me, one of our main
    priorities is the privacy of our visitors. This Privacy Policy document
    contains types of information that is collected and recorded by Random Bits
    of Wisdom and how we use it.</p>

<p>If you have additional questions or require more information about our
    Privacy Policy, do not hesitate to contact us.</p>

<p>This Privacy Policy applies only to our online activities and is valid for
    visitors to our website with regards to the information that they shared
    and/or collect in Random Bits of Wisdom. This policy is not applicable to
    any information collected offline or via channels other than this website.
</p>

<h2>Consent</h2>

<p>By using our website, you hereby consent to our Privacy Policy and agree to
    its terms.</p>

<h2>Information we collect</h2>

<p>The personal information that you are asked to provide, and the reasons why
    you are asked to provide it, will be made clear to you at the point we ask
    you to provide your personal information.</p>
<p>If you contact us directly, we may receive additional information about you
    such as your name, email address, phone number, the contents of the message
    and/or attachments you may send us, and any other information you may choose
    to provide.</p>
<p>When you register for an Account, we may ask for your contact information,
    including items such as name, company name, address, email address, and
    telephone number.</p>

<h2>How we use your information</h2>

<p>We use the information we collect in various ways, including to:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Provide, operate, and maintain our webste</li>
    <li>Improve, personalize, and expand our webste</li>
    <li>Understand and analyze how you use our webste</li>
    <li>Develop new products, services, features, and functionality</li>
    <li>Communicate with you, either directly or through one of our partners,
        including for customer service, to provide you with updates and other
        information relating to the webste, and for marketing and promotional
        purposes</li>
    <li>Send you emails</li>
    <li>Find and prevent fraud</li>
</ul>

<h2>Log Files</h2>

<p>Random Bits of Wisdom follows a standard procedure of using log files. These
    files log visitors when they visit websites. All hosting companies do this
    and a part of hosting services' analytics. The information collected by log
    files include internet protocol (IP) addresses, browser type, Internet
    Service Provider (ISP), date and time stamp, referring/exit pages, and
    possibly the number of clicks. These are not linked to any information that
    is personally identifiable. The purpose of the information is for analyzing
    trends, administering the site, tracking users' movement on the website, and
    gathering demographic information. Our Privacy Policy was created with the
    help of the <a href="https://www.privacypolicygenerator.info">Privacy Policy
        Generator</a> and the <a
        href="https://www.disclaimergenerator.org/">Disclaimer Generator</a>.
</p>

<h2>Cookies and Web Beacons</h2>

<p>Like any other website, Random Bits of Wisdom uses 'cookies'. These cookies
    are used to store information including visitors' preferences, and the pages
    on the website that the visitor accessed or visited. The information is used
    to optimize the users' experience by customizing our web page content based
    on visitors' browser type and/or other information.</p>

<p>For more general information on cookies, please read <a
        href="https://www.cookieconsent.com/what-are-cookies/">"What Are
        Cookies"</a>.</p>

<h2>Our Advertising Partners</h2>

<p>Some of advertisers on our site may use cookies and web beacons. Our
    advertising partners are listed below. Each of our advertising partners has
    their own Privacy Policy for their policies on user data. For easier access,
    we hyperlinked to their Privacy Policies below.</p>

<ul>
    <li>
        <p>Google</p>
        <p><a
                href="https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads">https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads</a>
        </p>
    </li>
</ul>

<h2>Advertising Partners Privacy Policies</h2>

<p><P>You may consult this list to find the Privacy Policy for each of the
    advertising partners of Random Bits of Wisdom.</p></p>

<p>Third-party ad servers or ad networks uses technologies like cookies,
    JavaScript, or Web Beacons that are used in their respective advertisements
    and links that appear on Random Bits of Wisdom, which are sent directly to
    users' browser. They automatically receive your IP address when this occurs.
    These technologies are used to measure the effectiveness of their
    advertising campaigns and/or to personalize the advertising content that you
    see on websites that you visit.</p>

<p>Note that Random Bits of Wisdom has no access to or control over these
    cookies that are used by third-party advertisers.</p>

<h2>Third Party Privacy Policies</h2>

<p>Random Bits of Wisdom's Privacy Policy does not apply to other advertisers or
    websites. Thus, we are advising you to consult the respective Privacy
    Policies of these third-party ad servers for more detailed information. It
    may include their practices and instructions about how to opt-out of certain
    options. </p>

<p>You can choose to disable cookies through your individual browser options. To
    know more detailed information about cookie management with specific web
    browsers, it can be found at the browsers' respective websites.</p>

<h2>CCPA Privacy Rights (Do Not Sell My Personal Information)</h2>

<p>Under the CCPA, among other rights, California consumers have the right to:
</p>
<p>Request that a business that collects a consumer's personal data disclose the
    categories and specific pieces of personal data that a business has
    collected about consumers.</p>
<p>Request that a business delete any personal data about the consumer that a
    business has collected.</p>
<p>Request that a business that sells a consumer's personal data, not sell the
    consumer's personal data.</p>
<p>If you make a request, we have one month to respond to you. If you would like
    to exercise any of these rights, please contact us.</p>

<h2>GDPR Data Protection Rights</h2>

<p>We would like to make sure you are fully aware of all of your data protection
    rights. Every user is entitled to the following:</p>
<p>The right to access – You have the right to request copies of your personal
    data. We may charge you a small fee for this service.</p>
<p>The right to rectification – You have the right to request that we correct
    any information you believe is inaccurate. You also have the right to
    request that we complete the information you believe is incomplete.</p>
<p>The right to erasure – You have the right to request that we erase your
    personal data, under certain conditions.</p>
<p>The right to restrict processing – You have the right to request that we
    restrict the processing of your personal data, under certain conditions.</p>
<p>The right to object to processing – You have the right to object to our
    processing of your personal data, under certain conditions.</p>
<p>The right to data portability – You have the right to request that we
    transfer the data that we have collected to another organization, or
    directly to you, under certain conditions.</p>
<p>If you make a request, we have one month to respond to you. If you would like
    to exercise any of these rights, please contact us.</p>

<h2>Children's Information</h2>

<p>Another part of our priority is adding protection for children while using
    the internet. We encourage parents and guardians to observe, participate in,
    and/or monitor and guide their online activity.</p>

<p>Random Bits of Wisdom does not knowingly collect any Personal Identifiable
    Information from children under the age of 13. If you think that your child
    provided this kind of information on our website, we strongly encourage you
    to contact us immediately and we will do our best efforts to promptly remove
    such information from our records.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
