<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elixir on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/elixir/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Elixir on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 07:45:20 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/elixir/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>iEx Is Dope!</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/24/iex-is-dope/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 07:45:20 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/24/iex-is-dope/</guid>
      <description>iEx (Elixir&amp;rsquo;s interactive shell) is pure dope! It helped bring my development efforts back to the &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s play and see what happens&amp;rdquo; level. Since Elixir modules are stateless and made up of pure functions, reloading a module is as easy as calling r MyModule inside iEx. During development, I&amp;rsquo;d try to keep one module called Demo, or Scratch, etc, where I&amp;rsquo;d do the quick and dirty setting up of things. This scratch module would usually have one function only, called demo or run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elixir Month</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/11/elixir-month/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 07:49:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/11/elixir-month/</guid>
      <description>Yes, the Elixir. I’ve decided to use the cold February weather, as well as the relative project calm, and see how far I can go with it.
But why Elixir and why just now? There are a few reasons. Actually, this is not my first encounter with the language or the Erlang/BEAM ecosystem. About a year ago, a colleague at work and I started doing lunch break walks, in which we discussed tech topics, beyond the scope of our current projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] You Can Think of Any Web Server as a Function</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 19:07:54 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</guid>
      <description>“You can think of any web server as a function. Each time you type a URL, think of it as a function call to some remote server. That function takes your request and generates some response. A web server is a natural problem for a functional language to solve.”
 Excerpt From Programming Phoenix by Chris McCord
Buy on Amazon
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Programming Phoenix  Don’t accept the compromise between fast and beautiful: you can have it all.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>