<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Bulgaria on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
        <link>https://preslav.me/tags/bulgaria/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Bulgaria on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 16:30:10 +0100</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/bulgaria/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Why Is Bulgaria So Poor?</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2019/12/20/why-is-bulgaria-so-poor/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 16:30:10 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/12/20/why-is-bulgaria-so-poor/</guid>
            <description>Note: What follows is my answer to question on Quora. I thought it might be worth sharing with my readers too.
This is perhaps an unpopular opinion, but for whatever it is worth, I am going to let my mind speak. I would like to emphasize on the fact that I am, and will always be a Bulgarian, despite my conscious choice to live and have business somewhere else.
The reason why Bulgaria is so poor has nothing to do with its nature and geographic location.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Note:</strong> What follows is my answer to <a href="https://www.quora.com/Why-is-Bulgaria-so-poor/answer/Preslav-Rachev">question on Quora</a>. I thought it might be worth sharing with my readers too.</p>

<hr />

<p>This is perhaps an unpopular opinion, but for whatever it is worth, I am going to let my mind speak. I would like to emphasize on the fact that I am, and will always be a Bulgarian, despite my conscious choice to live and have business somewhere else.</p>

<p>The reason why Bulgaria is so poor has nothing to do with its nature and geographic location. Neither, is it a lack of smart brains, creative artists, or strong athletes. It also isn’t (shocking to some) a lack of money and material possessions. Nope, it is none of those.</p>

<p>What makes Bulgaria so poor is <strong>the lack of a strong society and civic spirit</strong>. We might be smart as individuals, but as a society, we are below mediocre.</p>

<p>It is this lack of strong social norms, which has led our tiny nation from one bad choice to the next, living a sub-standard level of life for decades in a row. This lack of a strong society causes distrust and apathy. Those in turn, have managed to estrange people even further from one another, ultimately leading to the disintegration of our tiny nation. It is a vicious cycle.</p>

<p>It is easy to blame it on the politicians and the mafia, but remember, neither came to power alone. Our distrust and apathy let them be where they are today.</p>

<p>It is easy to blame it on the others, but when the time comes to pay our dues, invest in our common future, or take action to discourage grey economy, we are the first to hide back in the rat hole.</p>

<p>By not showing civic courage, the Bulgarian people (myself included) have been putting a nail after nail in the coffin holding our society, but it’s not too late to act. I see hope in many places, and this makes me look at opportunities to help.</p>

<p>So, yes, my friends, Bulgarians are poor. They can’t see how rich they could have been, had they given each other a hand, instead of sneaking behind the front door, looking through the peephole.</p>

<p>—</p>

<p>P.S. I fully realize that people like me are a big part of the problem. Yet, I also believe that in order to see the problem, one needs to have gotten out, only to return with fresh solutions. Sitting in the warm broth and complaining about daily life won’t help.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title></title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907131824/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2019 16:24:31 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907131824/</guid>
            <description>My new favorite coffee mug - a special &amp;ldquo;You Are Here&amp;rdquo; Starbucks edition featuring Bulgaria. From what I heard, also quite a rare collectible item.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My new favorite coffee mug - a special &ldquo;You Are Here&rdquo; Starbucks edition featuring Bulgaria. From what I heard, also quite a rare collectible item.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/07/1SkDWiS.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title></title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907011324/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 11:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907011324/</guid>
            <description>On the road again&amp;hellip;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the road again&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/07/TulqGYv.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Sofia&#39;s Trams</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2019/06/23/sofia-s-trams/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/06/23/sofia-s-trams/</guid>
            <description>It has been almost a decade, since I last set foot in the city center of Bulgaria’s capital, Sofia. Although I fly home regularly, Sofia’s Airport is just an intermediary stop on my ultimate route to my hometown.
This time was different. My wife and I flew for the wedding of one of our best friends, and since we had a whole day to spare, we decided to take a walk through the centre of the City of Trams.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been almost a decade, since I last set foot in the city center of Bulgaria’s capital, Sofia. Although I fly home regularly, Sofia’s Airport is just an intermediary stop on my ultimate route to my hometown.</p>

<p>This time was different. My wife and I flew for the wedding of one of our best friends, and since we had a whole day to spare, we decided to take a walk through the centre of the <em>City of Trams</em>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/06/Sofia Tram 1.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>For those who have never been in Sofia, trams are a major form of transportation here, the first line having been established back in 1901. Although Sofia citizens enjoy a modern (and surprisingly clean) subway, trams have long been one of the things that people usually associate the city&rsquo;s center with.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/06/Sofia Tram 2.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/06/Sofia Tram 3.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/06/Sofia Tram 6.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<hr />

<p>Read more about the history of tram transportation in Sofia:</p>






<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%; margin-bottom: 1rem">

  
  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex:1; background: url(https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/ee/Tatra_T6A5_Sofia.jpg); background-size:cover; background-position:center; min-height: 120px">
  </div>
  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trams_in_Sofia">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        Trams in Sofia - Wikipedia</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      Tram Tatra T6A5 on line 22</div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trams_in_Sofia">https://en.wikipedia.org | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
