<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
        <link>https://preslav.me/post/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 07:49:10 +0100</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://preslav.me/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Elixir Month</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/11/elixir-month/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 07:49:10 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/11/elixir-month/</guid>
            <description>Yes, the Elixir. I’ve decided to use the cold February weather, as well as the relative project calm, and see how far I can go with it.
But why Elixir and why just now? There are a few reasons. Actually, this is not my first encounter with the language or the Erlang/BEAM ecosystem. About a year ago, a colleague at work and I started doing lunch break walks, in which we discussed tech topics, beyond the scope of our current projects.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>Yes, the <a href="https://elixir-lang.org/" target="_blank">Elixir</a>. I’ve decided to use the cold February weather, as well as the relative project calm, and see how far I can go with it.</p>

<h2 id="but-why-elixir-and-why-just-now">But why Elixir and why just now?</h2>

<p>There are a few reasons. Actually, this is not my first encounter with the language or the Erlang/BEAM ecosystem. About a year ago, a colleague at work and I started doing lunch break walks, in which we discussed tech topics, beyond the scope of our current projects. My colleague is a big Elixir fan and has mentioned many times the advantages of Erlang and the BEAM VM. More than anything else, one thing struck me the most. All of the challenges that the cloud community of today is trying to tackle, such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>resilience</li>
<li>scalabiltiy</li>
<li>distribution</li>
<li>deployment</li>
</ul>

<p>etc, have already been thought about, and solved by a research group at Ericsson around three decades ago (albeit, at a smaller scale). Sure, Erlang is not an easy language to work with, but thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/josevalim" target="_blank">José Valim</a> and his work on Elixir, it wouldn’t even be necessary. So, about a year back, I took my first plunge.</p>

<h2 id="that-s-not-for-me">That’s not for me</h2>

<p>I got out of the water just as quickly as I got in there. Sure, Elixir is not nearly as obscure as Erlang, but it can be a bit overwhelming for the newcomer. Especially, if one is trying to swallow the whole OTP bit at the same time. At the time, I had discovered the simplistic philosophy of Golang, and despite all the alleged advantages, Elixir seemed way too much overhead. I (in)famously dismissed the language, as one where “the amount of punctuation might give you a headache”. Let alone the fact that similar to Java applications, Elixir ones also need the entire kitchen sink to be in place for an application to run. Compare this to a statically-bound Go app that you just throw onto a machine and you are good to go.</p>

<h2 id="crystal-enters-the-stage">Crystal enters the stage</h2>

<p>As a side note, I have to mention that part of why I dropped my initial foray into Elixir was because of a bias. I felt that it was too, Ruby-esque, whatever that must have meant to me at the time. I have somehow missed the early Ruby and Rails train around 15 years ago. My programming career set me on a different path. I have always been aware of Ruby’s community spirit, but only during the past year, did I come to appreciate the language and its writing aesthetic. Ironically, not through a Ruby itself, but via a wonderful derivative language, named <a href="https://crystal-lang.org/" target="_blank">Crystal</a>. I already went into more detail about Crystal <a href="https://preslav.me/2020/01/26/a-crystal-in-go-s-world/" target="_blank">in a previous post</a>.</p>

<p>The more I started dabbling into Crystal, the more I started looking at its inspiration - Ruby. Ruby is certainly not a language without flaws, and the community is trying to work on those. Partially, via addressing those issues at the core - Ruby 3.0 is expected to arrive <a href="https://bugs.ruby-lang.org/versions/5" target="_blank">at the end of this year</a>. Yet, others are taking what the language is best known for, and applying it to other paradigms - such as Elixir’s functional approach to programming.</p>

<h2 id="second-attempt-elixir-month">Second attempt: Elixir Month</h2>

<p>My second attempt to tackle Elixir seems to go much more smoothly than the first one. One day, I had the feeling that the constructs in the language just clicked for me- even the nasty OTP ones. I set out out a goal for myself to use Elixir for a month during February, and see how far I can go with it.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="some-starting-reources">Some starting reources</h2>






<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%">

  
  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex:1; background: url(https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1519435676i/38732242._UY630_SR1200,630_.jpg); background-size:cover; background-position:center; min-height: 120px">
  </div>
  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://gohugo.io/">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        Elixir in Action</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      The Elixir language blends the battle-tested power and stability of the Erlang virtual machine with an approachable and expressive syntax...</div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/38732242-elixir-in-action">https://www.goodreads.com | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

<p>Really, one of the best books on starting with Elixir. If you enjoy it, please help me support this site by <a href="https://amzn.to/2HFjtSR" target="_blank">buying it on Amazon</a>.</p>

<p>Let Saša Jurić himself convince you:

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/JvBT4XBdoUE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>
</p>


<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/gom6nEvtl3U" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>[Quote] You Can Think of Any Web Server as a Function</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 19:07:54 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</guid>
            <description>“You can think of any web server as a function. Each time you type a URL, think of it as a function call to some remote server. That function takes your request and generates some response. A web server is a natural problem for a functional language to solve.”
 Excerpt From Programming Phoenix by Chris McCord
Buy on Amazon
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Programming Phoenix  Don’t accept the compromise between fast and beautiful: you can have it all.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>“You can think of any web server as a function. Each time you type a URL, think of it as a function call to some remote server. That function takes your request and generates some response. A web server is a natural problem for a functional language to solve.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Excerpt From <em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26871792-programming-phoenix" target="_blank">Programming Phoenix</a></em> by Chris McCord</p>

<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2vkYthk" target="_blank">Buy on Amazon</a></p>

<hr />






<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%">

  
  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex:1; background: url(https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1444081913i/26871792._UY630_SR1200,630_.jpg); background-size:cover; background-position:center; min-height: 120px">
  </div>
  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://gohugo.io/">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        Programming Phoenix</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      Don’t accept the compromise between fast and beautiful: you can have it all. Phoenix creator Chris McCord, Elixir creator José Valim, and...</div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26871792-programming-phoenix">https://www.goodreads.com | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>A Crystal in Go’s World</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/26/a-crystal-in-go-s-world/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/26/a-crystal-in-go-s-world/</guid>
            <description>Imagine a programming language with the ergonomic syntax of Ruby, the speed of execution of C, the concurrency model of Go, and last but not least, a compiler that performs null checks at compile time. Sounds like a dream? Well, this language exists, but chances are, you haven’t heard of it so far.
Meet Crystal!
Crystal is all of the above, plus it has types, outstanding documentation, and a strong community, delivering a steady stream of new libraries (a.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>Imagine a programming language with the ergonomic syntax of Ruby, the speed of execution of C, the concurrency model of Go, and last but not least, a compiler that performs null checks at compile time. Sounds like a dream? Well, this language exists, but chances are, you haven’t heard of it so far.</p>

<p>Meet <a href="https://crystal-lang.org/" target="_blank">Crystal</a>!</p>


    <img src="/images/2020/image-crystal.png"  alt="Crystal home page"  class="center"  style="border-radius: 8px;"  />



<p>Crystal is all of the above, plus it has types, <a href="https://crystal-lang.org/reference/overview/" target="_blank">outstanding documentation</a>, and a strong community, delivering a steady stream of new libraries (a.k.a “shards”). Don’t get fooled by the current version number (0.32.1). Crystal has been around for quite a few years (since 2012) and has a mature set of language features and an ecosystem of good libraries.</p>

<h2 id="where-does-the-speed-come-from">Where does the speed come from?</h2>

<p>Crystal produces fast and lightweight native applications using the LLVM infrastructure. When I say fast, I mean, <a href="https://github.com/kostya/benchmarks" target="_blank">really fast</a>. Take the fastest Go code you can find and chances are, the same code in Crystal will perform at least on par with it, and often quite a bit faster. Measuring Crystal’s performance against that of Ruby makes no sense.</p>

<p>There are no runtime frameworks or virtual machines necessary. One can just grab the compiled binary and deploy it. When compared with deploying and running a Ruby application, this feels like a whole different league.</p>

<p>Note that there are some caveats, which I am going to discuss in a future blog post. For now, let’s just say that building and distribution are equally as easy, as those in Rust. As of yet, nothing can beat the Go compiler speed-wise, but my experience with the Crystal tooling has been more than pleasant so far.</p>

<h2 id="csp-style-concurrency">CSP-style concurrency</h2>

<p>One of the things that make Go so interesting is its concurrency model. The idea about goroutines that communicate via channels is based on an approach dating back to the late 1970s, called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communicating_sequential_processes" target="_blank">Communicating Sequential Processes (CSP)</a>. Crystal uses an analogous approach. Programs run in what is known as <a href="https://crystal-lang.org/reference/guides/concurrency.html" target="_blank">“fibers”</a>. The main fiber can spawn any number of concurrent fibers that send and receive data via blocking channels.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-crystal" data-lang="crystal">channel <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> Channel(Nil)<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>new 
spawn <span style="color:#66d9ef">do</span>    
	puts <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;Before send&#34;</span>    
	channel<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>send(<span style="color:#66d9ef">nil</span>)    
	puts <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;After send&#34;</span> 
<span style="color:#66d9ef">end</span>  

puts <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;Before receive&#34;</span> 
channel<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>receive 
puts <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;After receive&#34;</span></code></pre></div>
<h2 id="why-re-invent-ruby-in-2020">Why re-invent Ruby in 2020?</h2>

<p>The creators of Crystal obviously didn’t intend on changing the world of programming by creating a new language. They just <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20181126095302/https://manas.tech/blog/2016/04/01/the-story-behind-crystal.html" target="_blank">loved Ruby</a> and felt it sad to leave it for a more performant and type-safe alternative. Due to a series of trade-offs at the implementation level, Ruby is still slower and more memory-hungry than its competitors. Despite perfectly serving the needs of a large segment of Web users through Rails, its performance puts it at the back of the pack, when it comes to other use cases.</p>

<p>The point is fair and valid. As a language, Ruby has a concise and elegant syntax for writing. Once beyond the basic idioms, writing Ruby evokes pure joy. Crystal brings that joy to an even higher level through type-safety, native speed, and extremely simple concurrency model.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, I like Go too, precisely because of its verbosity and lack of idioms. When working with others on a big project, I’d prefer more ceremony and hoops, in the name of transparency and equal code comprehension. Different languages exist to serve different purposes and be used by different groups of people. The trick is knowing when to use and when the other.</p>

<h2 id="so-is-crystal-worth-having-a-look">So, is Crystal worth having a look?</h2>

<p>Absolutely! If only to know that it exists and keep an eye on it, I’d go check it out and write a few applications with it. Whether Crystal will take off in the future is a bit more difficult to say, however. As mentioned, the 99% resemblance to Ruby is nice, and so is the blazing-fast performance. Yet, I am missing the Crystal community’s drive towards more prominence. There has been a long-awaited move towards a 1.0 release, which is a crucial milestone and would surely bring in many newcomers. To my understanding, the language and its tooling are stable enough for a 1.0 release.</p>

<p>I understand that Crystal does not have the backing of either Google or Mozilla. Neither does it have multi-billion-dollar use-cases to put on its home page. I understand that fighting for the same space with Go, C/C++, and Rust is an unfair battle. Yet, I also believe that we’re long past the days when choosing one technology over another was a zero-sum game. All it needs is a little push.</p>

<p>I am hoping for the best!</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>[Quote] Manual Work is a Bug</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/18/quote-manual-work-is-a-bug/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/18/quote-manual-work-is-a-bug/</guid>
            <description>Here are a few lines from Manual Work is a Bug that I firmly stand by:
 The successful engineer has a quick way to create documents for new procedures and to find existing procedures. People with this mindset avoid the cognitive load of deciding whether or not a task is worth documenting, because they document everything. On finding a potential improvement, they are not slowed by the speed bump of switching from a document viewer to a document editor because they work from the editor at the start.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are a few lines from <em><a href="https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3197520" target="_blank">Manual Work is a Bug</a></em> that I firmly stand by:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The successful engineer has a quick way to create documents for new procedures and to find existing procedures. People with this mindset avoid the cognitive load of deciding whether or not a task is worth documenting, because they document everything. On finding a potential improvement, they are not slowed by the speed bump of switching from a document viewer to a document editor because they work from the editor at the start. Heck, they have a dedicated second monitor just for their editing app!</p>

<p>[…]</p>

<p>The successful engineer realizes that the earlier he starts collaborating, the sooner others can contribute. Together they can create a culture of documentation that spreads throughout the team. Thus, every project is collaborative and has a “stone soup” feeling, as all are invited to bring their skills and insights. The more people who embody this culture, the more success it has.</p>

<p>[…]</p>

<p>By creating a culture of continuous improvement, constantly taking baby steps along the four phases, the work becomes less stressful and easier to manage. While the other reasons listed here are quite logical, what motivates me to maintain this discipline is more emotional: I want to reduce stress and have more time for creativity and joy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>/Thomas A. Limoncelli/</p>






<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%">

  

  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex: 1 1 0%; background: rgba(0, 0, 0, 0) linear-gradient(#eaeaea 0%, #73747b 100%) repeat scroll 0% 0%; min-height: 120px;">
  </div>

  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://gohugo.io/">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        Manual Work is a Bug</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      </div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3197520">https://queue.acm.org | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Reflecting on My Experience With Go, One Year After</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/17/reflecting-on-my-experience-with-go-one-year-after/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/17/reflecting-on-my-experience-with-go-one-year-after/</guid>
            <description>In my little more than a year day-to-day developer experience with Go, I have so far learned three things:
 I can change my entire view of how programming works, even after 12+ years of doing it in one form or another. People are blaming Java for all the wrong reasons People are praising Go for all the wrong reasons  Let me explain. This post is not about saying that “language A is better than language B”, or vice versa.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>In my little more than a year day-to-day developer experience with Go, I have so far <strong>learned three things</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>I can change my entire view of how programming works, even after 12+ years of doing it in one form or another.</li>
<li>People are blaming Java for all the wrong reasons</li>
<li>People are praising Go for all the wrong reasons</li>
</ol>

<p>Let me explain. This post is not about saying that “language A is better than language B”, or vice versa. It is about asking ourselves the question why things work the way they do, and whether doing them differently is a bad, or potentially, good thing.</p>

<p>Before joining the Go camp, I had worked quite a few years as a Java developer, with all the stereotypes that this role could evoke in one’s head. I co-developed data-processing systems for various industries. Yet, much of the code I wrote was just boilerplate: passing data from one format to the other, or devising complex abstractions behind what should have really just been calling a function and obtaining its result. Yes, the code was difficult to comprehend, but I was proud of it for this exact reason. The more hoops I created, the more secure I felt that:</p>

<ol>
<li>I was doing what I thought was right</li>
<li>If people didn’t understand the code, they’d have to come to me for an advice, further boosting my ego.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-language-is-not-to-blame-for-this">The language is not to blame for this</h2>

<p>The fact that much of the existing Java code is full of bureaucracy has nothing to do with the language itself, or with its platform. Our developer community should bear the sole responsibility. I can assure anyone that perfectly functioning Java applications can be written without 90% of the ceremony. They will be smaller and run faster. Most probably, easier to comprehend, too. And yet, they won’t get you hired in any well-respected company. They just won’t pass the <em>developer prejudice</em> test. I know. I’ve seen many elegant solutions and rejected them for not being /idiomatic/ enough.</p>

<h2 id="go-isn-t-a-silver-bullet-either">Go isn’t a silver bullet either</h2>

<p>For much of the same reasoning, jumping ship towards Go, just because “it is not Java”, won’t bring anyone far. Even before I started writing Go, I had heard and read many stories, about how simple and fast it made everything, how little ceremony it had, compared to Java, how it would eventually kill all other languages, etc. All blah, blah. Despite all of the above being true, you have to discover the truth in each for yourselves. If you approach the language out of desperation with your current way of working, you’re going to be set for a rough path.</p>

<p>See, if you all you wanted was to get a faster running (name language of choice), you could certainly do it. Yet, holding on to the mental baggage of your previous experience will be hard and messy. My first Go project started out as a rewrite of a Spring Boot app I’d started earlier, so I thought I’d just organize it the same way. To keep the story short, let’s just say it was a spectacular disaster. Only after I started from scratch, did it really start taking off.</p>

<h2 id="go-is-a-language-without-with-less-idioms">Go is a language without (with less) idioms</h2>

<p>Let’s do a naive math experiment. Imagine that you could create valid programming expressions combining any 3 keywords, from a programming language’s vocabulary. Thus, if a language only has 10 keywords, the maximum number of possible expressions is 10 * 9 * 8 = 720. In contrast, a language, with, say, 20 keywords would end up having 20 * 19 * 18 = 6840 expressions. Twice as many keywords would result in almost 10 times as many expressions!</p>

<p>Languages tend to encourage the creation and use of idioms. With that many possible expressions, it’s a normal behaviour for an individual, or a group of people to start associating and using expressions for certain things. The problems usually occur when another group comes with its own way of expressing the same thing. Both are perfectly valid, but each group would have issues understanding the other.</p>

<p>This is not to say that Go having a very strict and concise nature, is totally devoid of idioms. That would be impossible. It is in our nature to try to associate and abstract certain concepts. Yet, when a language has a deliberately smaller vocabulary, the chances for different groups accidentally finding multiple ways of doing the same thing are smaller. This helps the communication between people a great deal, but comes with a very obvious downside. Code (or any written expression, for that matter) without idioms is very, very verbose.</p>

<p>So, whoever told you that Go is not a verbose language, probably either lied to you on purpose, or had’n really seen any other programming languages up until that point. But hey, we agreed that verbosity in the name of communication and common understanding is a actually a good thing, right?s</p>

<h2 id="go-is-a-test-for-senior-engineers">Go is a test for senior engineers</h2>

<p>A lot has been said about the initial concept about Go, and how the idea was to design a language for juniors fresh out of college, and with little programming experience. I think that understanding the beauty of going back to the roots of programming, can be a cathartic experience for many seasoned programmers.</p>

<p>See, junior programmers start with little baggage and preconceptions, so in their view, anything that can be done with code is fair and justified. Including, burning a CPU, or erasing a disk due to an arithmetic error.</p>

<p>Somewhere along the middle of the career path, a bunch of principles start to pile up. All of them out of the desire to step on what’s already been learned, and to make sure that things are smoothly and safely without immediate supervision. Learning and applying the principles is great, because it ensures a gradual path forward. But for many, it becomes a dogma which they blindly stick to, without asking whether a simpler alternative could be better.</p>

<p>The problem with principles is that they only work well around 80% of the time. It is the remaining 20% that can be disastrous for a project, or for one’s career. It is the understanding where to apply a principle, and where to deliberately throw it away in the name of pragmatism, which turns a software engineer into a senior software engineer.</p>

<p>To really appreciate Go, one needs to learn how to discern what makes it and its community stand out from the rest. One needs to go through a phase of utter disgust with the language, for it “lacking” certain feature. Moving on despite the urge to go back to a familiar ground, would result in one of two things:</p>

<ol>
<li>Make one realise that indeed, the Go language is not what they need or want</li>
<li>Learn to appreciate going back to the roots, as well as when to favour pragmatism over principles</li>
</ol>

<p>In any case, it would be an interesting experience.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Using Gohack for Temporary Modifications to Go Module Dependencies</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/10/using-gohack-for-temporary-modifications-to-go-module-dependencies/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 19:14:17 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/10/using-gohack-for-temporary-modifications-to-go-module-dependencies/</guid>
            <description>I started programming Go right at the time when the topic of modularization heated up. Of course, we all know how it all played out with Go modules. They are here and they are (IMO) great. I have spent a significant amount programming Python before virtual environments were really a thing, and believe me, things got really messed up at times.
One big disadvantage of modules is that one can’t really edit them.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started programming Go right at the time when the topic of <em>modularization</em> heated up. Of course, we all know how it all played out with Go modules. They are here and they are (IMO) great. I have spent a significant amount programming Python before virtual environments were really a thing, and believe me, things got really messed up at times.</p>

<p>One big disadvantage of modules is that one can’t really edit them. For a good reason, of course. You want them to be clean and reproducible, but occasionally, one needs to just insert a <code>log.Printf</code> or a tiny inspection function somewhere. One option is to call <code>mod vendor</code>, but this would copy all the dependencies to the vendor folder. Clearly, a lot more overhead than what one would need.</p>

<p>This is where <a href="https://github.com/rogpeppe/gohack" target="_blank">gohack</a> comes in really handy. It uses a clever feature of the Go modules, called /replace/. It allows the user to manually override the path to a given dependency. Instead of doing all of this manually, however, gohack will do it all for you.</p>

<p>After installing go-installing gohack, go to your module-bound Go project and use it instead of <code>go get</code> for a given dependency:</p>

<pre><code>gohack get example.com/foo/bar
</code></pre>

<p>gohack will fetch the code and store it in a special place inside your <code>$HOME</code> directory. It will also do the go.mod replacements for you:</p>

<pre><code>replace example.com/foo/bar =&gt; /home/me/gohack/example.com/foo/bar
</code></pre>

<p>All the edits you now do to the dependency that was added to your <code>$HOME</code> folder, will now affect the project that uses it.</p>

<p>Once you have done checking, and want to revert to using the original dependency, you can simply use the undo functionality:</p>

<pre><code>gohack undo example.com/foo/bar
</code></pre>

<p>or to revert all changes to all “hacked” dependencies:</p>

<pre><code>gohack undo
</code></pre>

<hr />






<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%">

  
  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex:1; background: url(https://avatars0.githubusercontent.com/u/66491?s=400&amp;v=4); background-size:cover; background-position:center; min-height: 120px">
  </div>
  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://gohugo.io/">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        rogpeppe/gohack</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      Make temporary edits to your Go module dependencies - rogpeppe/gohack</div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="https://github.com/rogpeppe/gohack">https://github.com | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>How to Request an App Refund on the Apple App Store</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2019/12/21/how-to-request-an-app-refund-on-the-apple-app-store/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/12/21/how-to-request-an-app-refund-on-the-apple-app-store/</guid>
            <description>Buying the wrong product happens all the time, and apps make no exception to that. Although it does not apply to every country, if you live within the EU, you have the right to ask for a full refund of your purchases, no strings attached. You can do that with apps you have bought from the App Store too, without having to provide an explanation. It is actually very easy, though providers ty to put a few stones on the way.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Buying the wrong product happens all the time, and apps make no exception to that. Although it does not apply to every country, if you live within the EU, you have the right to ask for a full refund of your purchases, no strings attached. You can do that with apps you have bought from the App Store too, without having to provide an explanation. It is actually very easy, though providers ty to put a few stones on the way. In the case of the App Store, I don’t think you can really do it from the app itself. You have to go to a special site instead:</p>

<p><a href="reportaproblem.apple.com" target="_blank">reportaproblem.apple.com</a></p>

<p>After signing in, you will see all the apps you have downloaded for free or purchased. Find the one you want to refund (assuming, you are within 14 days of the purchase). Click on “Report a Problem” (I know, you are actually exercising your rights, but just keep playing the game). Be careful to select the right option from the menu:</p>


    <figure class="left" >
        <img src="/images/2019/12/appstore1.png"   />

        
            <figcaption class="center" >The right option is down below</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



<p>See how far below the right option is? Anyway, once you choose it, there are no further obstructions. Just hit “Cancel Purchase” and you are good to go!</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/12/appstore2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/2019/12/appstore3.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Panic Without Worry</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2019/12/14/panic-without-worry/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/12/14/panic-without-worry/</guid>
            <description>In the Go community, there is some kind of paranoia around panicking, as if it’s the worst thing that can happen to your application. In fact, it often is the better option. Think about Go programs as CLI applications. Would you rather crash right away and let the user react, or hang, trying to recover? The same applies to applications running as services. Modern tooling makes it easy to automatically restart a crashing service within seconds.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Go community, there is some kind of paranoia around panicking, as if it’s the worst thing that can happen to your application. In fact, it often is the better option. Think about Go programs as CLI applications. Would you rather crash right away and let the user react, or hang, trying to recover? The same applies to applications running as services. Modern tooling makes it easy to automatically restart a crashing service within seconds.</p>

<p>When necessary, panic without worry.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>If You Can’t Get Flutter to Work with Your Beta Version of Xcode</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2019/11/11/get-flutter-to-work-with-beta-xcode/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/11/11/get-flutter-to-work-with-beta-xcode/</guid>
            <description>You need to explicitly set the beta version of Xcode as your default one via the command line:
sudo xcode-select -s /Applications/Xcode-beta.app/Contents/Developer/ Afterwards, getting your app to run via flutter run should work as it used to before.
Related Resources @media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   select - Managing Multiple Versions Of Xcode  It&amp;#39;s not uncommon developers to have multiple versions of Xcode installed.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>You need to explicitly set the beta version of Xcode as your default one via the command line:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">sudo xcode-select -s /Applications/Xcode-beta.app/Contents/Developer/</code></pre></div>
<p>Afterwards, getting your app  to run via <code>flutter run</code> should work as it used to before.</p>

<h2 id="related-resources">Related Resources</h2>






<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%">

  

  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex: 1 1 0%; background: rgba(0, 0, 0, 0) linear-gradient(#eaeaea 0%, #73747b 100%) repeat scroll 0% 0%; min-height: 120px;">
  </div>

  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://gohugo.io/">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        select - Managing Multiple Versions Of Xcode</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      It&#39;s not uncommon developers to have multiple versions of Xcode installed. For example, I typically have the latest beta as well as the most current</div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="http://iosdevelopertips.com/xcode/xcode-select-managing-multiple-versions-of-xcode.html">http://iosdevelopertips.com | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Why I Still Find the Minimap Useful</title>
            <link>https://preslav.me/2019/11/10/why-i-still-find-the-minimap-useful/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/11/10/why-i-still-find-the-minimap-useful/</guid>
            <description>This is an answer, I wrote in response to a recent blog post by Erica Sadun:
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   My enemy the Minimap  The minimap is one of Xcode 11’s starring features. I know many people were excited for it at its debut but after months of exposure, I now just disable it in the Adjust Editor Options menu (… https://ericasadun.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an answer, I wrote in response to a recent blog post by <a href="https://ericasadun.com" target="_blank">Erica Sadun</a>:</p>






<style scoped>
  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .embed-image {
      min-width: 100%;
    }
  }
</style>
<div
  style="display:flex; flex-wrap: wrap; border: 1px solid #d4d4d4; width:100%">

  
  <div class="embed-image"
    style="flex:1; background: url(https://ericasadun.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Screen-Shot-2019-11-08-at-8.07.45-AM.png); background-size:cover; background-position:center; min-height: 120px">
  </div>
  

  <div class="embed-content" style="flex:3; padding: 1rem;"><a
      href="https://gohugo.io/">
      <div class="title"
        style="font-weight: 800; margin-bottom: 1rem; font-size:120%">
        My enemy the Minimap</div>
    </a>
    <div class="embed-description" style="margin-bottom:1rem; font-size:80%">
      The minimap is one of Xcode 11’s starring features. I know many people were excited for it at its debut but after months of exposure, I now just disable it in the Adjust Editor Options menu (…</div>
    <div class="embed-meta" style="font-size:60%">
      <div style="float:left; max-width:80%"><a
          href="https://ericasadun.com/2019/11/08/my-enemy-the-minimap/">https://ericasadun.com | </a></div>
      <div style="float: right">Created with <a
          href="https://noembed.preslav.me/">NoEmbed</a></div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

<p>Many people ignore a particular use of the minimap - understanding the complexity of some portion of the code, without having to look at each line. In most languages, complexity increases with the level of nesting of code. This is usually difficult to estimate when reading the code itself, since the brain is focused on what the code does, rather than how nested it is. By obscuring the text, and leaving only a bird&rsquo;s-eye view of the layout, the minimap might help pinpoint parts of the code, needing improvement. It can be very helpful when working with someone else code, or with a code base, which you haven&rsquo;t touched in a while.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
