<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Startups on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://example.com/tags/startups/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Startups on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2019 10:20:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://example.com/tags/startups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://example.com/microblog/220920191020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2019 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://example.com/microblog/220920191020/</guid>
      <description>If you wake up on a Casper mattress, hail a Lyft to get to your desk at WeWork, use DoorDash to order lunch to the office, hail another Lyft home, and have Uber Eats bring you dinner, you have spent your entire day interacting with companies that will collectively lose nearly \$13 billion this year. Most have never announced, and may never achieve, a profit.
Too many consumer-tech companies nearing their public offerings are selling magic shows at a science fair.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://example.com/microblog/201905110736/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 05:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://example.com/microblog/201905110736/</guid>
      <description>Today, I caught this nice series of tweets by @benedictevans on the rise and demise of tech giants. Unlike smaller companies, those do not die abruptly, or in a direct fight with the competition. Instead, they get sidelined by smarter and more innovative upstarts.
The series starts with:
Tech monopolies tend not to fall like Rome. They fall like Venice. They’re still there, and no-one actually invades them, but the trade routes moved, the things that gave them power and wealth stop mattering, and they become just another city, and then a backwater.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>