<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Running on Preslav Rachev</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/running/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Running on Preslav Rachev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 05:54:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/running/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907040754/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 05:54:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907040754/</guid>
      <description>The short pause from running is over and I am back to action. First things first, I bought a new pair of running shoes:
Those are called Adidas Terrex Two Boa. They feature a very stiff, but sturdy underfoot part (because they are made for trail running), and an innovative lacing system called Boa. It was a bit of a love at first sight, but I amnot really sure, if I am going to get used to those shoes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sixtus Half-Marathon (Schliersee) 2019</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/05/17/sixtus-half-marthon-schliersee-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/05/17/sixtus-half-marthon-schliersee-2019/</guid>
      <description>Today, I took part in the Sixtus Half-Marathon near lake Schliersee for the third time in a row. Unlike last year, this time I started with a completely different strategy - keep it cool and let everyone else pass by me during the first third of the race. Seeing everyone else&amp;rsquo;s backs can be demotivating and requires a lot of patience and training.
   After the first 5-6K, having realized that I was really the last of the HM group, I started slowly picking up the pace.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/2019051111035/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/2019051111035/</guid>
      <description>This is one of the best movies about running I have seen in a while. Although I peaked at the half-marathon distance (21K), I do run for pretty much the reasons that motivate this guy to run 100 miles. I also fight the same daemons along the race, urging me to stop and quit all the time.
One thing I learned during the 3 years of active running:
 Distance running is 20% physical and 80% mental fitness.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>