<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quote on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/categories/quote/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Quote on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 19:07:54 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/categories/quote/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] You Can Think of Any Web Server as a Function</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 19:07:54 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</guid>
      <description>“You can think of any web server as a function. Each time you type a URL, think of it as a function call to some remote server. That function takes your request and generates some response. A web server is a natural problem for a functional language to solve.”
 Excerpt From Programming Phoenix by Chris McCord
Buy on Amazon
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Programming Phoenix  Don’t accept the compromise between fast and beautiful: you can have it all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] Manual Work is a Bug</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/18/quote-manual-work-is-a-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/18/quote-manual-work-is-a-bug/</guid>
      <description>Here are a few lines from Manual Work is a Bug that I firmly stand by:
 The successful engineer has a quick way to create documents for new procedures and to find existing procedures. People with this mindset avoid the cognitive load of deciding whether or not a task is worth documenting, because they document everything. On finding a potential improvement, they are not slowed by the speed bump of switching from a document viewer to a document editor because they work from the editor at the start.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[QUOTE]: Plastic Synapses Offer Hardware Alternative to Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/01/06/quote-plastic-synapses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 13:34:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/01/06/quote-plastic-synapses/</guid>
      <description>via Plastic synapses offer hardware alternative to neural networks | ArsTechnica
 A synapse—the connection between two neurons—consumes at most 100 femtoJoules per event. Once you realize that the entire human body is about the equivalent of an 120W light bulb, you can see that the efficiency of the brain is just astounding. [&amp;hellip;] This result has implications. If this research does turn out to be the way forward, neural networks will not operate faster than our own brains.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>