<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quote on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/categories/quote/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Quote on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 22:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/categories/quote/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: The Case for Apple to Postpone macOS 10.16 into 2021 </title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/04/01/quote-the-case-for-apple-to-postpone-macos-10-16-into-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/04/01/quote-the-case-for-apple-to-postpone-macos-10-16-into-2021/</guid>
      <description>With so many errors reported throughout the lifetime of macOS Catalina, it kind of makes sense for Apple to slow down a bit and work on polishing it. Moving towards new features without fixing the existing bugs might be disastrous for the macOS ecosystem. But again, that&amp;rsquo;s Apple we&amp;rsquo;re talkign about. Anything can be expected from Apple. Like, deprecating macOS altogether, and eventually, replacing it with some some sort of iOS hybrid.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: The President Is Trapped</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/30/quote-the-president-is-trapped/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 10:38:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/30/quote-the-president-is-trapped/</guid>
      <description>Here is a quote from:
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   The President Is Trapped  Trump is utterly unsuited to deal with this crisis, either intellectually or temperamentally. https://www.theatlantic.com |  Created with NoEmbed     The president will try to blame someone else—but in this case the “someone else” is a virus, not a Mexican immigrant or a reporter with a disability, not a Muslim or a Clinton, not a dead war hero or a family of a fallen soldier, not a special counsel or an NFL player who kneels for the national anthem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] You Can Think of Any Web Server as a Function</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 19:07:54 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</guid>
      <description>“You can think of any web server as a function. Each time you type a URL, think of it as a function call to some remote server. That function takes your request and generates some response. A web server is a natural problem for a functional language to solve.”
 Excerpt From Programming Phoenix by Chris McCord
Buy on Amazon
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Programming Phoenix  Don’t accept the compromise between fast and beautiful: you can have it all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] Manual Work is a Bug</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/18/quote-manual-work-is-a-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/18/quote-manual-work-is-a-bug/</guid>
      <description>Here are a few lines from Manual Work is a Bug that I firmly stand by:
 The successful engineer has a quick way to create documents for new procedures and to find existing procedures. People with this mindset avoid the cognitive load of deciding whether or not a task is worth documenting, because they document everything. On finding a potential improvement, they are not slowed by the speed bump of switching from a document viewer to a document editor because they work from the editor at the start.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] Ten Years of Erlang</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/07/10/quote-ten-years-of-erlang/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 10:28:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/07/10/quote-ten-years-of-erlang/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s probably not too important, in the grand scheme of things, whether you are using a language like Erlang or not. While I do feel it&amp;rsquo;s under-used and under-rated, the biggest benefit of it is not in running a system that uses it. The biggest benefit comes from learning about the fundamentals of solid system design, and internalizing its lessons in a practical context.
 @media (max-width: 640px) { .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] What Do I Know?</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/06/11/quote-what-do-i-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 10:12:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/06/11/quote-what-do-i-know/</guid>
      <description>I happen to know and have worked together with Dom. A really inspiring person, and one, whose opinions I often share. Particularly, this one on writing and sharing your knowdledge with the world:
 Don’t question whether something is advanced enough to share it. Don’t worry if that knowledge already exists on the internet. The only question you need to ask yourself is this:
What do I know?
 @media (max-width: 640px) { .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: The Dying Art of Disagreement</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/10/30/quote-the-dying-art-of-disagreement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 10:56:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/10/30/quote-the-dying-art-of-disagreement/</guid>
      <description>Here is a quote from:
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Opinion | The Dying Art of Disagreement  Today’s clashes may hoarsen our voices, but they rarely sharpen our thinking, much less change our minds. https://www.nytimes.com |  Created with NoEmbed     Intelligent disagreement is the lifeblood of any thriving society. Yet we in the United States are raising a younger generation who have never been taught either the how or the why of disagreement, and who seem to think that free speech is a one-way right: Namely, their right to disinvite, shout down or abuse anyone they dislike, lest they run the risk of listening to that person — or even allowing someone else to listen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[QUOTE]: Plastic Synapses Offer Hardware Alternative to Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/01/06/quote-plastic-synapses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 13:34:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/01/06/quote-plastic-synapses/</guid>
      <description>via Plastic synapses offer hardware alternative to neural networks | ArsTechnica
 A synapse—the connection between two neurons—consumes at most 100 femtoJoules per event. Once you realize that the entire human body is about the equivalent of an 120W light bulb, you can see that the efficiency of the brain is just astounding. [&amp;hellip;] This result has implications. If this research does turn out to be the way forward, neural networks will not operate faster than our own brains.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: 3 Ways to Better Understand Your Emotions</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2017/02/28/quote-three-ways-to-better-understand-your-emotions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 11:01:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2017/02/28/quote-three-ways-to-better-understand-your-emotions/</guid>
      <description>Here is a quote from:
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   3 Ways to Better Understand Your Emotions  Naming them is an important first step. https://hbr.org |  Created with NoEmbed     Anger and stress are two of the emotions we see most in the workplace — or at least those are the terms we use for them most frequently. Yet they are often masks for deeper feelings that we could and should describe in more nuanced and precise ways, so that we develop greater levels of emotional agility, a critical capability that enables us to interact more successfully with ourselves and the world</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>