<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Twitter on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/twitter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Twitter on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 22:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/twitter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Stay Focused on Twitter Despite All the Buzz</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/11/06/how-i-stay-connected-on-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/11/06/how-i-stay-connected-on-twitter/</guid>
      <description>With so much going on Twitter, we long have passed the point of being able to just look at our timelines and stay up-to-date. In fact, I have personally stopped following and would even go as far as to remove a significant portion of the people I’ve been following over the years.
From people to topics Before anyone gets offended by my supposed rudeness, let me clear up. I do get to stay up-to-date with a large variety of stuff on Twitter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905110736/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 05:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905110736/</guid>
      <description>Today, I caught this nice series of tweets by @benedictevans on the rise and demise of tech giants. Unlike smaller companies, those do not die abruptly, or in a direct fight with the competition. Instead, they get sidelined by smarter and more innovative upstarts.
The series starts with:
Tech monopolies tend not to fall like Rome. They fall like Venice. They’re still there, and no-one actually invades them, but the trade routes moved, the things that gave them power and wealth stop mattering, and they become just another city, and then a backwater.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Made a Mastodon Account and so Far I like It</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/08/19/i-made-a-mastodon-account-and-i-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/08/19/i-made-a-mastodon-account-and-i-like-it/</guid>
      <description>So, you might have heard about Mastodon. A micro-blogging alternative to Twitter, boasting itself for being 100% open-source, and for its decentralised nature.
  Unlike traditional social networks like Twitter and Facebook, Mastodon is not driven by a single company profiting by selling your identity to others, but by a network of instance maintainers and supporters who put their own money on the line. Ensuring that Mastodon is going to live in the long term sounds easy&amp;hellip;on paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Use Twitter More Efficiently with These Hidden Search Features</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/04/02/how-to-use-twitter-more-efficiently-with-these-hidden-search-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/04/02/how-to-use-twitter-more-efficiently-with-these-hidden-search-features/</guid>
      <description>Twitter can be a mess sometimes. If you follow tons of people, it’s easy to get lost in the torrent of constant updates. This was one of the reasons why Twitter decided to move away from the purely chronological timeline a couple of years ago. In a move that almost ditched the diehard Twitter fans in favor of the mainstream, predominantly passive content consumers, the company started pushing more and more in favour of algorithmically adjusted timelines, much like Facebook does it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>