<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Preslav Rachev</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Preslav Rachev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 23:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing DevNotes</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/03/09/introducing-devnotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/03/09/introducing-devnotes/</guid>
      <description>With a few short micro-post exceptions, my blog has been relatively quiet over the past month. The reason for this is simple. I have devoted much of my writing resources of the past weeks into a new site. A wiki called DevNotes.
That is right, I have started a separate writing project, parallel to my blog. Yet, before you start thinking that this is the end of the blog, don&#39;t worry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogroll intro</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/5d924197-f52f-4aa2-b84e-1e80be7fed7b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 08:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/5d924197-f52f-4aa2-b84e-1e80be7fed7b/</guid>
      <description>I have started disrupting the &amp;ldquo;Medium effect&amp;rdquo; by building a &amp;ldquo;blogroll&amp;rdquo; the good old way - simply linking to blogs of friends that I follow. The first ones to get on board are George Ho, Nikita Tonsky, and John Sundell. I will be adding more and more as time goes by.
With time, I am planning to add some more automation and clever aggregation of great content. I have a few surprises in the hat, but first things first, let&amp;rsquo;s build a network of connected blogs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First micro-post</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/725fca76-9dbb-46a3-867a-1863aa4880e7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/725fca76-9dbb-46a3-867a-1863aa4880e7/</guid>
      <description>This weekend, I moved this blog in what seems a small design step, but a serious milestone forward. I added the possibility to write micro-posts, or just about anything that is simply a passing thought, perhaps a sentence requiring no sentence whatsoever.
Not every post can, or even needs to be a few pages long, with a bunch of the research and heavy on media. Sometimes, the most ingenious messages hide in the simple, unfinished sentence.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>