<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 Cents on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/categories/2-cents/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2 Cents on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/categories/2-cents/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Few Broken Windows</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/10/10/a-few-broken-windows-apple-ios13/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/10/10/a-few-broken-windows-apple-ios13/</guid>
      <description>I have been using iOS 13 / iPadOS / watchOS 6 for a couple of weeks now. My general impression: something seems a bit off. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, the new features are great. I totally love the Dark Mode support, the new Notes features, etc. I also have managed to get through the whole update phase without any major issues. No iCloud syncing problems, no significant battery drain, no frequent restarts, or any of the kind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Frog</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/08/23/mind-the-frog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/08/23/mind-the-frog/</guid>
      <description>If you put a frog in a frying pan, it will quickly jump out. Yet, if you put the frog in cold water and slowly heat, the frog will enjoy the warmth until it&amp;rsquo;s too late to escape.
 We have all heard that story, but how many of us can admit that we play the frog on a daily basis? Especially at work, people tend to put a lot more focus on what they are working on and rather, avoid having a say on how the rest of the organization moves forward.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned in 2018</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/12/31/what-i-learned-in-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 16:51:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/12/31/what-i-learned-in-2018/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s that time of the year again. The time when you make yourself a cup of coffee, and go through the events of the past years, searching for a sign that it has been worth it. And judging by the numbers alone, it seems like a very eventful year:
In 2018, I:
 Got engaged Changed my job Started new new side projects Attended 4 conferences and countless meetups Had my own chance to present in front of an audience (twice) Visited 5 countries and met many new people Read 15 books Wrote nearly 30 blog posts Ran 626 km, and finished 4 half-marathons Made between 5,500 and 6,000 push-ups  Wow, quite a year, heh?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Made a Mastodon Account and so Far I like It</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/08/19/i-made-a-mastodon-account-and-i-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/08/19/i-made-a-mastodon-account-and-i-like-it/</guid>
      <description>So, you might have heard about Mastodon. A micro-blogging alternative to Twitter, boasting itself for being 100% open-source, and for its decentralised nature.
  Unlike traditional social networks like Twitter and Facebook, Mastodon is not driven by a single company profiting by selling your identity to others, but by a network of instance maintainers and supporters who put their own money on the line. Ensuring that Mastodon is going to live in the long term sounds easy&amp;hellip;on paper.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>