<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 Cents on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/categories/2-cents/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2 Cents on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:28:11 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/categories/2-cents/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Stay the F*** Home, Germany!</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/20/stay-the-f-home-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:28:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/20/stay-the-f-home-germany/</guid>
      <description>Judging by how much people in Munich seem to enjoy the sunny days of spring, I am going to conclude that either:
 they all live in complete denial of the situation they already gave up they fully trust that no matter what happens, the German healthcare system would fix them in no time. it’s sunny outside, so who cares  I’ve said it before, and I will say it once again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Step Outside the Comfort Zone</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/14/a-step-outside-the-comfort-zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 17:36:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/14/a-step-outside-the-comfort-zone/</guid>
      <description>Yes, the current situation sucks. Big time. It&amp;rsquo;s not good for anyone. Least of all, for the ones fighting for their lives, and those, doing their best to bring things back to normal. It needs patience and coordinated effort, but we&amp;rsquo;ll make it through, sooner or later. Patience and perseverance are hard, I know, but those are what has kept humanity moving forward. They would do so, for generations to come.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflecting on My Experience With Go, One Year After</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/17/reflecting-on-my-experience-with-go-one-year-after/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/17/reflecting-on-my-experience-with-go-one-year-after/</guid>
      <description>In my little more than a year day-to-day developer experience with Go, I have so far learned three things:
 I can change my entire view of how programming works, even after 12+ years of doing it in one form or another. People are blaming Java for all the wrong reasons People are praising Go for all the wrong reasons  Let me explain. This post is not about saying that “language A is better than language B”, or vice versa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Is Bulgaria So Poor?</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/12/20/why-is-bulgaria-so-poor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 16:30:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/12/20/why-is-bulgaria-so-poor/</guid>
      <description>Note: What follows is my answer to question on Quora. I thought it might be worth sharing with my readers too.
This is perhaps an unpopular opinion, but for whatever it is worth, I am going to let my mind speak. I would like to emphasize on the fact that I am, and will always be a Bulgarian, despite my conscious choice to live and have business somewhere else.
The reason why Bulgaria is so poor has nothing to do with its nature and geographic location.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Few Broken Windows</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/10/10/a-few-broken-windows-apple-ios13/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/10/10/a-few-broken-windows-apple-ios13/</guid>
      <description>I have been using iOS 13 / iPadOS / watchOS 6 for a couple of weeks now. My general impression: something seems a bit off. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, the new features are great. I totally love the Dark Mode support, the new Notes features, etc. I also have managed to get through the whole update phase without any major issues. No iCloud syncing problems, no significant battery drain, no frequent restarts, or any of the kind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Frog</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/08/23/mind-the-frog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/08/23/mind-the-frog/</guid>
      <description>If you put a frog in a frying pan, it will quickly jump out. Yet, if you put the frog in cold water and slowly heat, the frog will enjoy the warmth until it&amp;rsquo;s too late to escape.
 We have all heard that story, but how many of us can admit that we play the frog on a daily basis? Especially at work, people tend to put a lot more focus on what they are working on and rather, avoid having a say on how the rest of the organization moves forward.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned in 2018</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/12/31/what-i-learned-in-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 16:51:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/12/31/what-i-learned-in-2018/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s that time of the year again. The time when you make yourself a cup of coffee, and go through the events of the past years, searching for a sign that it has been worth it. And judging by the numbers alone, it seems like a very eventful year:
In 2018, I:
 Got engaged Changed my job Started new new side projects Attended 4 conferences and countless meetups Had my own chance to present in front of an audience (twice) Visited 5 countries and met many new people Read 15 books Wrote nearly 30 blog posts Ran 626 km, and finished 4 half-marathons Made between 5,500 and 6,000 push-ups  Wow, quite a year, heh?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Made a Mastodon Account and so Far I like It</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2018/08/19/i-made-a-mastodon-account-and-i-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2018/08/19/i-made-a-mastodon-account-and-i-like-it/</guid>
      <description>So, you might have heard about Mastodon. A micro-blogging alternative to Twitter, boasting itself for being 100% open-source, and for its decentralised nature.
  Unlike traditional social networks like Twitter and Facebook, Mastodon is not driven by a single company profiting by selling your identity to others, but by a network of instance maintainers and supporters who put their own money on the line. Ensuring that Mastodon is going to live in the long term sounds easy&amp;hellip;on paper.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>