<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book on Preslav Rachev</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/book/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book on Preslav Rachev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 16:11:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906251911/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 16:11:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906251911/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Adults in the Room&amp;rdquo; by Yanis Varoufakis
 That which feels to many like a conspiracy of the powerful is simply the emergent property of any network of super black boxes.
 Adults in the Room    What happens when you take on the establishment? In this blistering, personal account, world-famous economist Yanis Varoufakis blows the ...
Source: - https://www.goodreads.com   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906231845/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 15:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906231845/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;The Three-Body Problem&amp;rdquo;:
 &amp;ldquo;The universe is a hollow sphere floating in the middle of sea of fire. There are numerous tiny holes in the surface of the sphere, as well as a large one. The tiny ones are the stars, and the large one is the sun.&amp;rdquo;
 The Three-Body Problem (Remembrance of Earth’s Past #1)    The Three-Body Problem is the first chance for English-speaking readers to experience this multiple award winning phenomenon from China&amp;#39;s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906111300/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 11:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906111300/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Without Their Permission&amp;rdquo; by Alexis Ohanian:
 “Building an audience doesn’t require a large advertising budget, certainly not at the beginning. Making something people want—something that people love, that solves a real problem they have in an elegant way—is the most effective thing one can do to generate buzz. There’s no secret to “going viral,” despite what plenty of self-appointed “social media gurus” may tell you (hint: if they call themselves that, run in the opposite direction).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2018 21:13:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</guid>
      <description>Opportunities are whispers, not foghorns.
If we can&amp;rsquo;t hear their soft rhythms - if we are to busy rushing about, waiting for thunderclaps of revelation, inspiration, and certainty - or if we can spot them but can&amp;rsquo;t nurture them into real advantages, then we might as well be blind to them.
 From the book &amp;ldquo;Nikola Tesla: Imagination and the Man That Invented the 20th Century&amp;rdquo;
Nikola Tesla    If you want to learn about one of history’s most fascinating minds and uncover some of his secrets of imagination—secrets that enabled hi.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>