<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/book/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 16:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote]: Developer Hegemony: The Future of Labor</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/04/15/quote-developer-hegemony-the-future-of-labor/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/04/15/quote-developer-hegemony-the-future-of-labor/</guid>
      <description>A quote from the amazing book &amp;ldquo;Developer Hegemony&amp;rdquo; (Buy on Amazon) by Erik Dietrich:
 You need to stop viewing yourself as a software engineer II or a QA specialist or a dev manager. You need to stop viewing yourself as an employee of your (or any) company and start viewing yourself as the owner of your personal brand and operation. You are an island. You are other.
 How many of you, dear readers think this way?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] You Can Think of Any Web Server as a Function</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 19:07:54 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/02/10/quote-you-can-think-of-any-web-server-as-a-function/</guid>
      <description>“You can think of any web server as a function. Each time you type a URL, think of it as a function call to some remote server. That function takes your request and generates some response. A web server is a natural problem for a functional language to solve.”
 Excerpt From Programming Phoenix by Chris McCord
Buy on Amazon
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Programming Phoenix  Don’t accept the compromise between fast and beautiful: you can have it all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201909021700/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 16:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201909021700/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;The Mom Test&amp;rdquo; by Rob Fitzpatrick
 It’s not anyone else’s responsibility to show us the truth. It’s our responsibility to find it.
 @media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   The Mom Test  The Mom Test is a quick, practical guide that will save you time, money, and heartbreak. They say you shouldn&amp;#39;t ask your mom wh... https://www.goodreads.com |  Created with NoEmbed    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201908211824/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 16:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201908211824/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Without their Permission&amp;rdquo; by Alexis Ohanian
 We like to think that real talent always has a way of getting noticed. Harrison Ford was a self-taught professional carpenter when he as hired to build cabinets in the home of George Lucas, who cast him in American Graffiti and set him on a course that led to Indiana Jones. If Ford hadn’t picked up the right hammer or taken another job, Solo would’ve ended up saying “I love you, too”, instead of “I know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906251911/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 16:11:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906251911/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Adults in the Room&amp;rdquo; by Yanis Varoufakis
 That which feels to many like a conspiracy of the powerful is simply the emergent property of any network of super black boxes.
 @media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Adults in the Room  What happens when you take on the establishment? In this blistering, personal account, world-famous economist Yanis Varoufakis blows the .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906231845/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 15:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906231845/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;The Three-Body Problem&amp;rdquo;:
 &amp;ldquo;The universe is a hollow sphere floating in the middle of sea of fire. There are numerous tiny holes in the surface of the sphere, as well as a large one. The tiny ones are the stars, and the large one is the sun.&amp;rdquo;
 @media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   The Three-Body Problem (Remembrance of Earth’s Past #1)  The Three-Body Problem is the first chance for English-speaking readers to experience this multiple award winning phenomenon from China&amp;#39;s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906111300/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 11:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906111300/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Without Their Permission&amp;rdquo; by Alexis Ohanian:
 “Building an audience doesn’t require a large advertising budget, certainly not at the beginning. Making something people want—something that people love, that solves a real problem they have in an elegant way—is the most effective thing one can do to generate buzz. There’s no secret to “going viral,” despite what plenty of self-appointed “social media gurus” may tell you (hint: if they call themselves that, run in the opposite direction).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2018 21:13:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</guid>
      <description>Opportunities are whispers, not foghorns.
If we can&amp;rsquo;t hear their soft rhythms - if we are to busy rushing about, waiting for thunderclaps of revelation, inspiration, and certainty - or if we can spot them but can&amp;rsquo;t nurture them into real advantages, then we might as well be blind to them.
 From the book &amp;ldquo;Nikola Tesla: Imagination and the Man That Invented the 20th Century&amp;rdquo;
@media (max-width: 640px) { .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>