<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Micropost on Preslav Rachev</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/categories/micropost/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Micropost on Preslav Rachev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2019 05:45:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/categories/micropost/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/220503190745/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2019 05:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/220503190745/</guid>
      <description>I caught myself using my old Android phone more and more these days. A 5-year-old Nexus 5, that is. I dug it out a few weeks ago. After the fresh reset all the service updates, it works as if it hasn’t been two years since I last used it for real. Trinkering with Android like in the good old days felt exciting. In comparison, my experience with iOS has always been like living a comfortable, but relatively boring life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/220420191020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/220420191020/</guid>
      <description>Good morning from Augsburg, Germany 👋🏼 Not many people around (expected for the second day of Easter), but we got a beatufil sunshine and a great view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Untitled)</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/4c0cda7e-6f05-4cca-95eb-a69f3dd22cbe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 06:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/4c0cda7e-6f05-4cca-95eb-a69f3dd22cbe/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I finally bought the full license for Alfred. I have been looking at Alfred for several years now, never really coming to the impulsive decision to actually buy the license. I have been relatively happy with what Launchbar offers, event in the free version, but Alfred Workflows are a whole different game. These are definitely the most well-invested 25 EUR I have put on a piece of software for a while.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Untitled)</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/1c6e082d-f7f2-4c84-98bf-3387c0ed0a29/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 15:08:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/1c6e082d-f7f2-4c84-98bf-3387c0ed0a29/</guid>
      <description>There are certain podcasts, which I’ve mostly listened to while running. The thing is, every time I listen to any of them while not running, my mind immediately shifts back to the trail. I guess, this makes me a slightly more developed version of Pavlov’s Dog 😂</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogroll intro</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/5d924197-f52f-4aa2-b84e-1e80be7fed7b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 08:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/5d924197-f52f-4aa2-b84e-1e80be7fed7b/</guid>
      <description>I have started disrupting the &amp;ldquo;Medium effect&amp;rdquo; by building a &amp;ldquo;blogroll&amp;rdquo; the good old way - simply linking to blogs of friends that I follow. The first ones to get on board are George Ho, Nikita Tonsky, and John Sundell. I will be adding more and more as time goes by.
With time, I am planning to add some more automation and clever aggregation of great content. I have a few surprises in the hat, but first things first, let&amp;rsquo;s build a network of connected blogs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First micro-post</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/725fca76-9dbb-46a3-867a-1863aa4880e7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/725fca76-9dbb-46a3-867a-1863aa4880e7/</guid>
      <description>This weekend, I moved this blog in what seems a small design step, but a serious milestone forward. I added the possibility to write micro-posts, or just about anything that is simply a passing thought, perhaps a sentence requiring no sentence whatsoever.
Not every post can, or even needs to be a few pages long, with a bunch of the research and heavy on media. Sometimes, the most ingenious messages hide in the simple, unfinished sentence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/06482203-14be-4333-a9c1-398461d66c7c/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/06482203-14be-4333-a9c1-398461d66c7c/</guid>
      <description>A view to live for! 😍
Sendlinger Tor | Munich</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>