<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 Cents on Random Bits of Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/2-cents/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2 Cents on Random Bits of Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 17:36:59 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/2-cents/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Step Outside the Comfort Zone</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/03/14/a-step-outside-the-comfort-zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 17:36:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/03/14/a-step-outside-the-comfort-zone/</guid>
      <description>Yes, the current situation sucks. Big time. It&amp;rsquo;s not good for anyone. Least of all, for the ones fighting for their lives, and those, doing their best to bring things back to normal. It needs patience and coordinated effort, but we&amp;rsquo;ll make it through, sooner or later. Patience and perseverance are hard, I know, but those are what has kept humanity moving forward. They would do so, for generations to come.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflecting on My Experience With Go, One Year After</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2020/01/17/reflecting-on-my-experience-with-go-one-year-after/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2020/01/17/reflecting-on-my-experience-with-go-one-year-after/</guid>
      <description>In my little more than a year day-to-day developer experience with Go, I have so far learned three things:
 I can change my entire view of how programming works, even after 12+ years of doing it in one form or another. People are blaming Java for all the wrong reasons People are praising Go for all the wrong reasons  Let me explain. This post is not about saying that “language A is better than language B”, or vice versa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Is Bulgaria So Poor?</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/12/20/why-is-bulgaria-so-poor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 16:30:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/12/20/why-is-bulgaria-so-poor/</guid>
      <description>Note: What follows is my answer to question on Quora. I thought it might be worth sharing with my readers too.
This is perhaps an unpopular opinion, but for whatever it is worth, I am going to let my mind speak. I would like to emphasize on the fact that I am, and will always be a Bulgarian, despite my conscious choice to live and have business somewhere else.
The reason why Bulgaria is so poor has nothing to do with its nature and geographic location.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Still Find the Minimap Useful</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/11/10/why-i-still-find-the-minimap-useful/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/11/10/why-i-still-find-the-minimap-useful/</guid>
      <description>This is an answer, I wrote in response to a recent blog post by Erica Sadun:
@media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   My enemy the Minimap  The minimap is one of Xcode 11’s starring features. I know many people were excited for it at its debut but after months of exposure, I now just disable it in the Adjust Editor Options menu (… https://ericasadun.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/2019102111035/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/2019102111035/</guid>
      <description>Estimates are such a loaded and dangerous endeavor for an engineer. To the point where companies mistakenly talk about estimates like its a “skill” that an engineer can learn. But the reality is that if you can make a probabalistically accurate estimate, then its likely that the task should have been automated by some other means already.
 @media (max-width: 640px) { .embed-image { min-width: 100%; } }   Dear Startup: You have no idea how much that costs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Few Broken Windows</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/10/10/a-few-broken-windows-apple-ios13/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/10/10/a-few-broken-windows-apple-ios13/</guid>
      <description>I have been using iOS 13 / iPadOS / watchOS 6 for a couple of weeks now. My general impression: something seems a bit off. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, the new features are great. I totally love the Dark Mode support, the new Notes features, etc. I also have managed to get through the whole update phase without any major issues. No iCloud syncing problems, no significant battery drain, no frequent restarts, or any of the kind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Code is Boring</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/09/21/good-code-is-boring/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/09/21/good-code-is-boring/</guid>
      <description>You have seen them many times. Small snippets of code and the question &amp;ldquo;What would the the following piece of code print&amp;rdquo; beneath. You might have tried taking a guess, and perhaps, even failed.
#golang pop quiz: what will this print? https://t.co/99xR8wybpp pic.twitter.com/Q7YpJbYr8c
&amp;mdash; ✕✕✕✕✕ (@peterbourgon) May 18, 2017  I find those kinds of questions utterly pointless. They not only teach you nothing about real-world programming, but might also lead many newcomers to long-term frustration with programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Quote] Ten Years of Erlang</title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/2019/07/10/quote-ten-years-of-erlang/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 10:28:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/2019/07/10/quote-ten-years-of-erlang/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s probably not too important, in the grand scheme of things, whether you are using a language like Erlang or not. While I do feel it&amp;rsquo;s under-used and under-rated, the biggest benefit of it is not in running a system that uses it. The biggest benefit comes from learning about the fundamentals of solid system design, and internalizing its lessons in a practical context.
 @media (max-width: 640px) { .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905121007/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2019 08:07:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905121007/</guid>
      <description>Google: Here is somewhat of a premium phone (Pixel 3) for $800
Customers: Go Home, Google, you’re drunk.
Google: Here is a plastic version of the same phone with less features and slower hardware (Pixel 3a) for $400
Customers: it’s the best Take my money!
Google: Tricked ya!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905110736/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 05:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905110736/</guid>
      <description>Today, I caught this nice series of tweets by @benedictevans on the rise and demise of tech giants. Unlike smaller companies, those do not die abruptly, or in a direct fight with the competition. Instead, they get sidelined by smarter and more innovative upstarts.
The series starts with:
Tech monopolies tend not to fall like Rome. They fall like Venice. They’re still there, and no-one actually invades them, but the trade routes moved, the things that gave them power and wealth stop mattering, and they become just another city, and then a backwater.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>