<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quote on Preslav Rachev</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/quote/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Quote on Preslav Rachev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/quote/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/2019102111035/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 08:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/2019102111035/</guid>
      <description>Estimates are such a loaded and dangerous endeavor for an engineer. To the point where companies mistakenly talk about estimates like its a “skill” that an engineer can learn. But the reality is that if you can make a probabalistically accurate estimate, then its likely that the task should have been automated by some other means already.
 Dear Startup: You have no idea how much that costs.    The problem</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/280920191021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 11:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/280920191021/</guid>
      <description>Kickstarter has made its position clear. It is against unions. It opposes its workers’ effort to organize. It will not be changing its mind. It will be fighting its own staff and its project creators. Now, Kickstarter’s users must make their position clear. We will not tolerate union-busting. We will not give our money to a company that does it. We demand that the company reverse its position and commit to voluntarily recognizing the union if a majority of workers signal support.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/260920191021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 11:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/260920191021/</guid>
      <description>Chiefly, Go sacrifices expressiveness for uniformity.
The general principle is to favour the transparent and ready-to-hand over the remote and opaque, the concrete and literal over the abstract and magical. It’s like speaking a language without metaphors.
Learning Go won’t teach you any exciting new computer science concepts, or introduce you to a whole new paradigm of software development (for that, try Idris). But it will give you a better understanding of the breadth and variety of the design space for programming languages, at a time when mainstream languages generally seem to be converging (Kotlin is rather like Swift, is rather like Typescript, etc).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/260920191020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/260920191020/</guid>
      <description>Despite being a video-focused platform, people are increasingly coming to YouTube to look for podcasts. A recent survey of Canadian adults found that 43 percent of people “went to YouTube for podcasts in the past year.” That put YouTube ahead of Apple Podcasts (34 percent) and Spotify (23 percent).
Some of the top podcasts on YouTube are pulling in millions of views every few days or weeks. Top shows, like Ethan and Hila Klein’s H3 Podcast or Joe Rogan’s Joe Rogan Experience, have dedicated audiences who use YouTube notifications as an RSS feed, letting them know when a new episode is available to watch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/220920191020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2019 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/220920191020/</guid>
      <description>If you wake up on a Casper mattress, hail a Lyft to get to your desk at WeWork, use DoorDash to order lunch to the office, hail another Lyft home, and have Uber Eats bring you dinner, you have spent your entire day interacting with companies that will collectively lose nearly \$13 billion this year. Most have never announced, and may never achieve, a profit.
Too many consumer-tech companies nearing their public offerings are selling magic shows at a science fair.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201909021700/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 16:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201909021700/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;The Mom Test&amp;rdquo; by Rob Fitzpatrick
 It’s not anyone else’s responsibility to show us the truth. It’s our responsibility to find it.
 The Mom Test    The Mom Test is a quick, practical guide that will save you time, money, and heartbreak. They say you shouldn&amp;#39;t ask your mom wh...
Source: - https://www.goodreads.com   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201908211824/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 16:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201908211824/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Without their Permission&amp;rdquo; by Alexis Ohanian
 We like to think that real talent always has a way of getting noticed. Harrison Ford was a self-taught professional carpenter when he as hired to build cabinets in the home of George Lucas, who cast him in American Graffiti and set him on a course that led to Indiana Jones. If Ford hadn’t picked up the right hammer or taken another job, Solo would’ve ended up saying “I love you, too”, instead of “I know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 21:13:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</guid>
      <description>Japanese websites don&amp;rsquo;t look like trash because the designers wanted to do this. They look this way because the Japanese audiences like this. They like the huge and distracting flashing banners. They like the overwhelming amount of text. They like what you and I might call crass and unpolished advertising masquerading as website content.
 Why doesn’t Japan excel in software as they did in hardware?    Ah… Finally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906251911/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 16:11:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906251911/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Adults in the Room&amp;rdquo; by Yanis Varoufakis
 That which feels to many like a conspiracy of the powerful is simply the emergent property of any network of super black boxes.
 Adults in the Room    What happens when you take on the establishment? In this blistering, personal account, world-famous economist Yanis Varoufakis blows the ...
Source: - https://www.goodreads.com   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906231845/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 15:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906231845/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;The Three-Body Problem&amp;rdquo;:
 &amp;ldquo;The universe is a hollow sphere floating in the middle of sea of fire. There are numerous tiny holes in the surface of the sphere, as well as a large one. The tiny ones are the stars, and the large one is the sun.&amp;rdquo;
 The Three-Body Problem (Remembrance of Earth’s Past #1)    The Three-Body Problem is the first chance for English-speaking readers to experience this multiple award winning phenomenon from China&amp;#39;s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906211000/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 08:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906211000/</guid>
      <description>It’s amazing — amazing I say — how little generics are missed. To date, Go remains the small, simple language that fogies like me can remember Java being. I suppose that can’t last, but for now, I can pop open almost any .go file and if I can’t understand it pretty quick, the chances are very high that the problem is in the code not me.
 ongoing by Tim Bray · Go Creeping In    I’ve seen the inside of the Google and Amazon tech stacks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906111300/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 11:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906111300/</guid>
      <description>A quote from &amp;ldquo;Without Their Permission&amp;rdquo; by Alexis Ohanian:
 “Building an audience doesn’t require a large advertising budget, certainly not at the beginning. Making something people want—something that people love, that solves a real problem they have in an elegant way—is the most effective thing one can do to generate buzz. There’s no secret to “going viral,” despite what plenty of self-appointed “social media gurus” may tell you (hint: if they call themselves that, run in the opposite direction).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905011824/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 16:24:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905011824/</guid>
      <description>I felt that Go strikes the balance of robust systems programming and great performance with almost zero investment, and great developer experience. Some of that old 90’s feel, and a lot of that modern fantastic development practices.
 My Key Learnings after 30,000 LOC in Rust - Dotan Nahum - Medium    For me, Rust takes a stroll over the memory lane above and picks and drives home the best experiences from all those languages — which is a</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2018 21:13:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201830111824/</guid>
      <description>Opportunities are whispers, not foghorns.
If we can&amp;rsquo;t hear their soft rhythms - if we are to busy rushing about, waiting for thunderclaps of revelation, inspiration, and certainty - or if we can spot them but can&amp;rsquo;t nurture them into real advantages, then we might as well be blind to them.
 From the book &amp;ldquo;Nikola Tesla: Imagination and the Man That Invented the 20th Century&amp;rdquo;
Nikola Tesla    If you want to learn about one of history’s most fascinating minds and uncover some of his secrets of imagination—secrets that enabled hi.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>