<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Apple on Preslav Rachev</title>
    <link>https://preslav.me/tags/apple/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Apple on Preslav Rachev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 09:29:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://preslav.me/tags/apple/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907241129/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 09:29:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201907241129/</guid>
      <description>Apple is becoming a macOS gatekeeper too.
 For the past 35 years, any Mac developer who wanted to ship an update directly to customers could do so by recompiling a binary and distributing it. When macOS 10.15 ships this fall, the status quo will change. Mac developers must register with Apple and sign their products. They must submit their binaries to Apple for notarization. And most significantly of all, they must agree to the terms of Apple’s App Store developer contracts, even if they don’t distribute their apps through the App Store.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906081458/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 12:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201906081458/</guid>
      <description> Q: Aesthetically, what do you think about the design of the new grater?
A: It has been optimized for softer cheeses 😂
   329: Mac Pro Day — Accidental Tech Podcast — Overcast    Our live show from WWDC 2019!
Source: - Overcast   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905240633/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 04:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://preslav.me/microblog/201905240633/</guid>
      <description>Apple introduced on Tuesday a new line of MacBook Pros with supposedly, a more durable keyboard, and the latest gen Intel chips. The 15&amp;rsquo; version features an 8-Core CPU and up to 32 GB of RAM and up to 4 TB SSD. It&amp;rsquo;s a beast with an incredible performance:

Have no illusions however. All this power comes at a cost. An what a cost! I went to the Apple website and configured myself a top-of-the-line MBP with all the specs pushed to the max.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>